中英字幕by:Ocean-藏心    推荐指数:★★★
简介: 介绍了ListView的方方面面,但是内容有点老
再加上翻译比较粗糙,本来是3.5星,就推荐成3星吧
大家下午好
Good afternoon everyone
欢迎来到"ListView的世界"
and welcome to the world of ListView
我是Romain Guy
my name is Romain Guy
我是工作在Google的一位Android工程师
and i'm an Android Engineer at Google
我主要开发UI工具包和做一些其他的工作
i work on UI toolkit and few other things
我旁边的这位是Adam Powell,他也是Google的工程师
and joining me today's Adam Powell,is also an Engineer at Google
也工作在UI开发包这个组
he works also on UI toolkit
如果ListView曾令你抓狂过
and if you've ever been mad at ListView
那么这很有可能是我的不是或者是他的不是
it's probably my fault and or his fault
因此,如果在这个座谈会中,你有事想让我们知道
so if you have a thing to tell us into the session
尽管来告诉我们好了
come talk to us and you can
我们可以满足你的任何要求
do whatever you want to us
在我们会谈开始之前
before we get started
我们在线上有Google Wave,
你可以在我俩的演讲过程中分享出你的笔记
we have a Google Wave where you can share notes though the presentation
你也可以在线上问问题
you can also ask questions
你也可以对他人问的问题进行表决
you can vote on questions asked by other people
你也可以给那些不好的问题投差评
you can also down those questions that you think are stupid
Url已经显示在屏幕上了
and here is the url
我们希望大家能记住它
we want you will be able to see it
所以你现在可以把它记下来,如果你现在来不及
so try to write it down,if you don't have time to write it down right now
稍后我们会把幻灯片上传到网上
we will put the slide up in the session
你还可以去GoogleIO的网站,来寻找这个Wave的链接
you can also go to Google IO website and there is link to that Wave
在我们的会谈过程中,我们会现场回答Wave上的一些问题
and we will also take live questions of course
大家都有谁用过ListView啊
so how many of you have ever used ListView
作为一个Android开发者,请举手
as developer in the Android application,raise your hand
这有点令人小害怕啊,不过这很好
that's a scary and good
大家都有谁觉得ListView有点难用啊
how many of you have found ListView to be difficult to use
你们没举手的都是在骗人吧
you are the ones are lying
大家都有谁觉得ListView就应该是"这么难用"呢
and how many have used (i've a swore at) ListView in the best should is
呦.我瞄到了一些人羞怯的伸手,这挺好,挺好的
yeah,i see some timid hands,that's good,that's good
这说明你们在用ListView做着一些复杂的东西
that means you're doing some complex stuff with it
对于没有用过ListView的同志们
for those of you've never used ListView
ListView可是Android中一个相当普遍的UI控件呢
i mean it's a pretty common widget on Android
它几乎用于我们发布的每个App中
it uses in i think almost every application we ship
请看左边显示的
and you can see an example here in the slide on the left side
这是我们ApiDemo中的一个Demo,这个Demo中仅仅是
that's one of our ApiDemo,so it just stacks
把Item中的控件一项一项按垂直方向堆积起来
widgets vertically
大多数情况下,ListView仅仅展示简单的文本
most of the time,ListView shows simple text
或者显示文本+图标,
但是你还可以用ListView做更复杂的事情
(sometimes you have) icon and text,but you can do very very complex (though ListViews)
在我们android 1.0发布之前,我们有一版Gmail
before we ship android 1.0 actually,we had the version of Gmail
当你打开一封邮件后
where when you open the Email
我们用了由WebView填充的ListView
we were using a ListView made of WebViews
来展示邮件往来的对话内容
to display conversation
但是后来我们就没有这样做了,因为那种方法虽然ok
we stop doing that,because it works
但是那并不是很好用
but it's not that great to use
除非你想做一些非常非常疯狂的事情,你才可以这样干
but if you really want do something really crazy,you can
除了干简单的事情之外
and of course
你还可以用ListView干一些很复杂的事情
you can also do some very complex things with ListViews
在右边,你看到的是我写的一个实例App
so on the right side,you see an example,an App i wrote
这个App自定义了一个ListView,
实际上这是GridView,它俩很相似的
that customizes a ListView is actually a GridView which is very similar
你可以
and you can
自定义它们(ListView,GridView)的背景,
你可以自定义它们的选择状态
customize the background,you can customize the selection
你可以自定义非常非常复杂的Item项来填充其内容
you can have a very complex item inside the (shelf)
我先给大家提个醒,今天我们这里讲的任何内容
and just for the...i note that everything we're gonna talk about today
适用于ListView的同时,也适用于GridView
applies to ListView but also applies to GridView
有几项是专门针对ListView的
there is a couple of things that are (special) to ListView
但是
but
其他的大多数特性都也适用于GridView
pretty much everything applies to GridView as well
因此如果你用到GridView的时候
so if you've ever need a GridView
你可以把我们这次会谈以及这次的幻灯片当成开发参考
you can refer to this talk,you can refer to the slides
ListView跟GridView可以说是完全一样的
and everything will be the same
这里列出了我们这次会谈的议题
so here's are agenda for the session
我们要谈的方面有适配器,可视化
we gonna talk about adapters and visualization
以及ListView工作的基本原理
and how basically ListView works inside
然后我们会谈到你该如何的自定义ListView的条目
then we will gonna see how you can customize items
关于这方面涉及的是Item的各种属性
this is the item properties
再往下是表头跟表尾,以及视图选择器(Selector)
then headers and footers,we'll gonna talk about selectors
最后,我们会以一些其他特性来结束对ListView的讲解
then we gonna finish the talk with a few other features
还有你对ListView绝对绝对不能做的事情
and what you should never ever ever do with a ListView
在最后一个幻灯片时,我会接受
and i will asked showing the last slide
各位现场观众的提问
who amongst the audience
如果ListView真的让你抓狂的话
is doing the things that you should never doing are really mad you
那么,Adam就开始从适配器讲起了
so Adam is going to starts with adapters
好的
ok
这里涉及的问题是当数据集很大的时候
so the problem present here is dealing with large data sets
具体来说,当展示这些大数据集的时候
specifically presenting those large data sets
如果你有1万条数据项时
if you have ten thousand items available to you
你如何将这1万条数据显示在你的ListView中呢,
使得用户能对这些数据项进行操作
how do you get that on screen so that the user can proves them
用户可以很随意的得到任意一项
so that you can get through them relatively quickly
那么,问题在于处理大数据集时,内存的性能至关重要
the typically challenges for dealing with that is memory in performance
你肯定不想一下子将1万条数据项
全绑定到你的视图层级结构中
you don't want we attach ten thousand of views into your view hierarchy
这种情形下,视图这种对象是相当重量级的
views are fairly heavy wight objects in that sense
但是你还想要"飞划"它们66(溜溜- -!)的
and you want to be able to fling though them quickly
人们会对触摸设备有一种期望
people really sort of expect to be able to
那就是可以在这些设备上快速的找到想要的内容
navigate things quickly on touch screen devices specially
我们在ListView中提供的解决方案是
so the solution that we've implemented in ListView
我们仅仅按需填充ListView的数据项
is that we populate use on demand
因此我们只在
so we only bring up new views
需要新视图时引进它
as they are actually needed
那些不准备在屏幕上做显示的视图
nothing actually gets added to the view hierarchy
是不会被添加到视图的层级结构中的
that isn't going to be able to display on screen
其次,我们对视图层级结构中的视图进行了循环利用
secondly,we recycle those views
我们重用我们已经创建过的视图
so we reuse the views that we've already created
我们在重用时仅仅更改其内容而不改变其形态
and just filing new content as they come through
这样做有助于性能的提升
this help us address a lot of performance issue that come up
当你在上下循环快速划滚ListView时
when you're cycling through things very quickly
当你飞划往下看内容时
when you fling through a very long list
我们先来看几个术语
so a little bit terminology to start off with
由于有很多不同的方法来引用数据
just because there's a lot different ways to refer data
当你运用ListView时
when you working with a ListView
当我们谈到"索引"时
when we talk about an index
我们谈的是在视图层级结构中的视图组中的孩子视图
we are talking about child views within the ViewGroup
in the hierarchy
如果你调用getChildAt
so if you're calling getChildAt()
来获取一个视图的话
to go ahead fetch a view that's there
此时传入的参数就是index
that's when we talking about indexes
当我们说position时
when we talking about position
我们谈的是某个元素在你的适配器中所处的位置
we were talking about position of an element within your adapter
最后,当我们谈到id时
and finally,when we talk about ids
每个在适配器中的数据项可以有一个唯一的标识
each item within the adapter can have a unique identifier
用它可以来引用存放在适配器中的数据值
that refers to the value of the data store there
某些操作会使得这三个概念变得混淆起来
so if things start shuffling around
当你在适配器中执行插入或者删除操作时
you perform insertions and deletions on the data that's back
这些操作改变了你的底层数据集
that's backing in your adapter
这时,PPT上Stable IDs就显得比较有用了
then (this slide) are still a few extra tricks
当你的适配器有固定的ids时
when you have stable ids
你可以通过Adapter的hasStableIds方法返回true
when you tell the ListView that you have stable ids
来告诉ListView,你的id是固定的
by returning true from your adapter's hasStableIds()
这样,我们就会做一些额外的工作
then we were able to perform a few extra tricks that just makes the
注:CursorAdapter的hasStableId返回true,BaseAdapter为false
来让ListView记录所有id的变化情况.
the presentation a little bit nicer
注:可以参考ListView源码中hasStableId的语句来理解这里的意思
这样当很多元素被添加或者移除时
when a lot of elements get add or remove
我们可以尽力保持在屏幕上的数据项的id固定不变
we can trying keep the data relatively stable on screen
理解"索引","位置","标识"都是用来干啥的是很重要的
and understanding what the index,position and id do is very important
我觉得ListView的文档有点垃圾
because (i got meet) the documentation of ListView is somewhat lacking
这是俺们的错误,俺很对不住大家
to (Remain Polite),and it's turned our fault,we are very sorry
但是,我们对于
but we've been very careful
参数的取名是相当相当小心的
with respect to the naming of our parameters
因此不论何时你看到某个方法,他的参数里有"位置"
so whenever you see a method that talks about position
或者某个把"索引"作为其参数的方法
or you see a parameter of a method that's called index
你应该知道,参数是个什么名字,它就代表这种含义
you know,it's guaranteed that it's gonna be those meanings
在这方面,我们是尽力而为的.
everything is pretty good in that regard
必须的
definitely
那么
so
Adapter中数据项的展示始于getView方法的调用
the meet of your adapter is going to be the getView method
这个方法会将你的数据从数据源那里取出
this is what takes your data from your data source whatever that may be
不管这个数据源是来自网络
whether be something that you're fetching from network
还是来自本地数据库
something from a database that's local
这都无所谓
doesn't matter what it is
getView这个方法给予你对数据展示的全权控制
getView() gives you full presentation control of your data
你可以返回任意的View,这个View将成为ListView中的元素
you can return any arbitrary view and that becomes your element within the ListView
so
在getView的这个过程中,我们做了很多的优化工作
within getView(),we are offer a lot of opportunities to optimize this entire process
由于为了符合我们的优化策略,
我们会对开发者的行为做一些假设
and kind of to go along with that,because we make assumptions in order to make these optimizations
所以如果你的行为跟我们的假设不符,
你可能就搬起石头砸自己的脚了
there is a lot of opportunities to (shoot) yourself in the foot
我确信大伙中某些人会遇到过以下的情况
and i'm sure that some of you have come cross one or more of these before
为啥我不能点击到那个元素
why can't i click on this element that
这个元素是某个列表数据项中的一个孩子视图,
其位于父视图下面很远(估计是不可视)
that's a child far down in this particular list item
这里就牵扯到我们所做的假设,我们一会就来分析为什么
we'll get in (assume) that,we will get into why
更具象一点,我们会告诉大家
and specifically we will get into the fairly narrow
在任何getView中,你应该干的几件事儿
subset of things that you should be doing with any getView()
好
oh
那我就开讲了
so
ListView会"自作聪明"
ListView tries to be smart
正如你所见,它有时的确聪明过头了
as you can see,it's fairly easy to out smart here and there
但是
but
在getView中,我们传递进去了一个参数叫convertView
through getView(),we pass an extra view param call convertView
我们谈到过,ListView会复用其数据项的视图
we talk about how ListView end up reusing some of these views
当你快速飞划的时候
as you fling through data quickly
convertView是我们得以复用视图的关键
convertView is how it makes that happen
ListView会对所有移出屏幕(不可见)的视图进行记录
ListView will keep track of all the extra views they're moving off screen
之后,当下次getView的时候,就返回给你一个记录过的视图,
来让你用数据填充它,从而达到复用的效果
and then give you one back to fill out with your existing data
这个返回的被记录过的视图就是convertView
this is the convertView parameter that we saw on the slide here
这个过程也自动的匹配了数据项的类型
so this automatically match up item types for you as well
如果在你的Adapter中,你有多种不同的数据类型的话
if you have multiple different types of data within your adapter
返回的convertView也会正确的返回相应的ViewType
then convertView will always be the correct type
只要你告诉ListView,
你的Adapter每个位置的ViewType是什么就OK
as long as you tell ListView what type each position in your adapter is
这点我们一会也会说道说道
we will get to that (in) a little bit as well
因此
so
如果传递给getView的convertView不是null的话
if the convertView parameter pass to your getView() is not null
亲,一定要重用它.这会使你的应用性能大幅提升
please,reuse it.it's going to help the performance (of) your application quiet a bit
有多种不同的方式来实现getView
so there are different ways to implement the getView()
这里我们介绍三种不同的方式
we gonna see three of the different method
分别是慢方式,正确方式,以及快方式
there is the slow way,the correct way,the fast way
首先,大家先快速浏览一下PPT上的内容
so first of all,look at this slide really quickly and
接下来,是该举手的时候了
please raise your hand and that's ok,don't be ashamed
如果你曾经这样写getView的话,就举手
if you've ever written the getView() like this
我肯定有人这么干过
(i wanna).. i'm sure somebody have done it
哦,有了,这样咱屋里至少有了一个诚实的人
ok,at least there is someone honest in the room
这儿也有呢
you see more,we here too
这种实现方式是很幼稚的
so this is the naive way you would implement getView
因为你创建了一个新的视图
you've just created a new View
在每次调用getView的时候
every time getView is invoked
在第二行,
so you can see here at line No.2
我们从XML中通过反射创建了一个新的视图
we were inflating a View from XML
这个操作是很昂贵的,我们不得不解析XML
this is a very expensive operation we have to parse the XML
尽管这个过程我们优化了一遍又一遍
and even though this is highly optimize on Android. (it still takes)
但是这仍然需要相当多的时间,我们要实例化视图
quiet bit of time,we have to initialize the view we have to
还要给视图分配视图
allocate the memory
当要反射的View是由多个子视图组成是,那花费会相当高
it can be very costly when the view is made of sub views
拿这个例子来说,我们反射的View
so here for instance,the view when inflating in that example
是一个线性布局,其中包含了一个ImageView和TextView
is a LinearLayout that contains an ImageView and a TextView
一旦我们创建了这个视图
once we've created it
在第3和第4行
in line 3 and 4,we just
我们还绑定了数据到这两个视图之上
bind some data to do those two views so
我们在TextView上填充了文本,ImageView上设置了图片
we put some text in the TextView,an image in the ImageView
之后,我们把我们建好的View返回
then we return the view we've created
这里最大的问题是
now the big problem with that is
如果用户飞划这个列表时
if the user is flinging the list
当用户试着滑动上千条数据项时
and it's trying to scroll through thousand of items
这样我们就要创建上千的视图了
then we will gonna create thousands of those views
这内存花销肯定不小
which is gonna take a lot of memory
为了给大家一个清晰的认识
to give you an idea
一个视图在Android系统中大约会占用1到2K的内存
a view on Android cost about 1KB or 2KB of RAM
如果你有上千条视图
if you have a thousand of views,that's
这就有1M的内存被你浪费了
already 1MB RAM that's you're wasting
这意味着垃圾回收器
which means the garbage collector is gonna
垃圾回收器将会停止你的UI线程
it's gonna stop your UI thread
这将使动画呆滞
it's gonna make the animation stutter
那用户作何感想,肯定会对你的应用感到失望
and the user will be really (be sad at) your application
你可别不相信
don't believe that
列表中含有上千条数据项是罕见的
list a thousand of items are weird
因为就我而言,我就知道很多人
because for instance,i know many people
他们的通讯录中就有上千个联系人呢
we have thousands of contacts in the address book
坐拥上千联系人很随意,
当你把你的电子邮件程序设置成
it's very easy to do when your email application set to
快速存储联系人时,每当你回复Email的时候,
联系人就自动保存到你的通讯录中了
quick contacts automatically whenever you reply to an email
因此,为了解决这个问题
so to fix this,it's
就正如我们提及的,你只需重用这个convertView就行
like we mention,you just have to reuse convertView
因此,只需简单的检查一下
so simply check whether our view is
参数中的convertView是否为空
whether or not the convertView is null
如果是空,那么你就需要新建一个视图
if it's null,then you have to create a new view
你可以通过从XML中反射来创建也可以在程序中直接创建
you can inflate it from XML,you can create the view programmatically
不管你怎么创建,你必须要创建一个新的视图
do whatever you want,but you have to create a new view
另一方面
in the other case
如果convertView已经存在了,那么你就只需重用它即可
if the convertView is already available,just reuse it
正如我们所说到的,我们保证返回的convertView的类型
就是你所需要的视图类型
like we said we guarantee that convertView is the type of view that you want
因此,你知道其中会含有你的TextView
so you know that gonna have your TextView
你知道其中会含有你的ImageView
you know that gonna have your ImageView
这样做会使程序跑的非常快
and this is going to be much faster
从根本上来说,使用这个方式
basically,with this method
你仅需要分配来填充整个屏幕的视图数量的视图内存
you're going to allocate only the number of views you need to fill the screen
有时这个数量是1或者2,但是
sometimes you gonna allocate like one or two more,but
大多数情况下,这个数量可能会是7个,拿Nexus One来说的话
most of the time you're gonna be only like 7 all these views on the Nexus One for instance
俺说的话可是很现实的呦
so it's very (real)
不过,咱儿这儿还有下一个优化技术
now,there is another technique to
来使getView的实现更快一些
to make that implementation go faster
这个更好的实现方式是用了一个叫ViewHolder的类
it's a better way that we called a ViewHolder that
这个类是在Android团队开发1.0b之前开发的
we developed on the Android team just before 1.0b
因为那时我们遇到了性能方面的阻碍
cause we were running into performance issues
尤其是在通讯录这里
especially with address books
上千条的联系人
full of thousands of contacts
那么用ViewHolder能更快的原理在于
so the idea is that
你将会创建一个小型的数据结构在你的应用程序中
you're gonna create a small data structure in your application
这个数据结构会把数据静态存储在程序中
that is going to hold data that's static
这里的数据指的就是列表中每行的视图们
for each given row of the list
因此,在刚才的例子中
so in that example
对于每个列表中的数据项
for each item in the list
我们是用findViewById来找
we are doing a findViewById()
TextView和ImageView的
to find a TextView and an ImageView in line's 5 and 6
为啥我们要不断的通过这种方法来做成千上万次呢
so why should we bother doing it you know thousands of times
当我们处于一个大的数据列表中时
as with call though (in a) big list
因此,我们干脆一劳永逸的把找到过的保存起来
so instead we're just gonna hold things once and forever
保存到这个叫做ViewHolder小型类中,这个类你在哪创建都行
in this little class called ViewHolder so you can create it wherever you want
不过要把这个类变成静态的
try to make that class static
因此你不能把他创建在封闭实例中
so you don't (create) the enclosing instance
这就是ViewHolder的原理了
and this is how what occur looks like
当你使用ViewHolder的时候
when you you use the ViewHolder
这个方式跟上一种唯一不同的是,
当convertView是空的时候,你创建新视图时
so the only difference that when you create a new view when the convertView is null
此时,你创建你ViewHolder的实例
you create your instance of the ViewHolder
之后,你把ViewHolder中的各个视图给找到
you do the work of finding the children of the views
这里,我们找的是TextView和ImageView
so here we find the TextView and the ImageView
这是第5行到第9行的内容
so that's line 5 to 9
之后你把holder作为convertView的tag设置上去
then you can set the holder as the tag for the view
tag,仅仅是一种随机的对象
so the tag is just a random object
它可以是任何你想要的东西,你都可以将其设置到tag上
it can be anything you want that you can put it on the view
这里我们用tag的这个特性来存储额外的数据
and we use the tag facility here store extra data
当你有一个convertView传给ListView时
when you have a convertView that (backs) to you by ListView
你就可以用convertView来获取tag,
这样你就获取到了ViewHolder
you simply get the tag,you gets it as a ViewHolder
之后,我们看16和17行
then you should look lines 16 and 17
我们可以直接获取TextView和ImageView了
you can see that we access the TextView and the ImageView directly
因此我们把findViewById的花费给节省下来了
so we save the cost of doing the findViewById
这是一个很简单的例子
this is a very simple example
不过,在一些其他的应用中,你可以设置更多的数据
but in some applications,you can store even more data in there
比方说你可以存储字符串来做数据库查询
you can store for instance char arrays to do a (database) queries
来避免额外给查询语句分配空间来执行查询
to avoid allocating new arrays of characters every time you do a query
这里显示了3种方式的性能对比
and this is the comparison of the performance of the 3 methods
这些数据我们是从Froyo设备上获得的
so we took those numbers using a the Froyo (xx)
这个版本你们现在还不能得到
of Android that you guys don't have yet
这里的getView运行在
so this is running
更快的CPU上,因为这是在Nexus One上测试的
with a fast CPU cause we were on the Nexus One
我们创建了一个有1万项数据项的列表
and we create a list of 10,000 items
每个数据项在一个线性布局中,包含一个TextView和ImageView
each item in a LinearLayout that contains an Image and a TextView
按照最笨的实现方式,我们得到的结果是20帧每秒
with the Dumb boy,so with the dumb implementation of getView,we get about 20 frames per second
当我们复用convertView后
when we implement getView correctly by reusing the convertView
我们能达到50帧每秒
we go up to 50 frames per second
最后,当我们用上ViewHolder后,
我们达到了55帧每秒的性能
and finally when we use the ViewHolder we go up to 55 frames per second
这是个什么样的概念,给你个感性认识,在Nexus One上
to give an idea on the Nexus One
我们能达到的最大帧数是60帧每秒
the max number of frames per second you can get is 60
如果你把一些别的开销也算进去的话
so when you take it into account the overhead of just
比方说,重绘整个视图层级的开销
redrawing the view hierarchy
命令消息的传递,以及绑定视图
issuing all the commands,binding the views
还有加载位图等等
reading the bitmaps stuff like that
这几乎是你能达到的最大速度了
this is pretty much as fast as you can go
在你的Adapter里
inside that adapter
因此,如果你的程序能达到这样的速度
so if you can reach those numbers inside your application
你算是过关了,如果你是处于左边的,那么继续努力吧
you are good to go if you were on the left side,then keep working
ok
正如我之前提到的
so as i mention before
有很多时候,你会搬起石头砸自己的脚
there is a lot ways you shoot yourself in the foot during this process
大多数情况是,
most,it has to do with trying to
你在getView的实现过程中,过于聪明了,
想当然的去干一些事情来为自己做优化
out smart the way the getView tries to optimize things for you
因此,你不能创建任何局部的视图缓存
so don't create any sort of local view cache
不要试着自作聪明的说,"好,
don't try and be smart and say,"ok,well
我知道位置1肯定会是这个元素,
i know the position one is always going to be this element
因此我要在我的适配器中保存这个视图
so i'm just gonna save this view (via) in my adapter
这样无论何时我请求位置1这个元素时,
适配器总能正确的返回那个视图
always return this whenever i ask for position one
这里的问题在于
the problem with is that
由于ListView内部的循环器的实现方式
due to the implementation of the recycler inside ListView
如果你在getView中没有返回一个新建的View的话
if you're not passing back ether a new view that was just created
或者你没有把convertView这个实例返回
or exactly the convertView instance was passed to you
我们就假定依附在ListView上的其他任何东西是不可用的
it's going to assume that anything else whosever attached to the ListView is dead
ListView就会跳过这些东西,以及丢掉这些
and it just gonna go ahead and throw it away
有时,ListView会以一种很奇怪的方式对视图进行重新依附
now,sometimes this can end up getting reattached in really strange ways
这样以来,问题并不会马上出现
and it won't always look like there is a problem at first
直到ListView产生一些很奇怪的行为
until you start observing some very strange behavior
因此
so
首先不要局部缓存视图
don't cache views locally like that
其次不能在适配器中访问你缓存的视图
and don't access views from the adapter that way
同时,不要改变convertView的结构
don't change convertView structure either
不能因为系统传递给我一个视图
just because you have a view coming in
我就可以随意额外的添加或者删除视图的内容
that doesn't necessarily mean that you need to be adding or removing extra content from that view
这样的规范是为了适应系统的特性
that's the type system  for
实际上,我们可以做到传递给你的convertView就是
we can actually have convertView pass you back
你所需的视图类型,并且这个convertView
的所有子视图都已经初始化过了
exactly the type of view that you need that already has all these other subviews initialized for you
仅仅因为你的适配器中有不同类型的数据
so just because you have different types of data within your adapter
注:请参考API中Adapter的getViewTypeCount,和getView的说明
并不意味着你可以尝试去
doesn't necessarily mean that you need to try to
执行特定的操作来改变convertView的结构
perform all sorts of manipulations on convertView when it comes in
最后请注意,不要对getView的调用做任何预判
and lastly,don't make assumptions about getView calls
我们已经看到过某些开发者这样做,"那好,
we've seen developers try to do things like,"ok
getView现在刚从位置5调用过了
getView was just called for position 5
那么我就要存储一些关于
so i'm going to store something about
这个在位置5处的视图实例的东西
this particular view instance is position 5
我将把此视图实例缓存在别的地方
以便我下次可以直接获取
and i'm gonna cache that in some place just so that i can refer back to that view quickly
无论何时背后数据更新过以后
whenever data it behind updates
此处的问题在于
the problem with this is that
所有getView的调用的顺序是乱序的
the order of getView calls isn't guaranteed
因为我们可能在底层这样来调用getView
so we may end up calling getView behind the scenes
为了测量ListView到底能有多大
to go ahead and measure out how big the ListView can be
出于性能的考虑,我们可能会用到
被扔掉过的convertView来做测量的参考
and we might do this with a throw-away convertView that were passing to you,again,for performance reasons
因此
so
那么你最终获取到的视图
the view that you get
我们最后一次调用的getView所传递进去的convertView
the last view that you get passed to you for a position
实际上有可能不是最后一个将要屏幕上将要显示的View
may not actually be the one that ends up on screen later on
事实上,这儿有一个很棒的例子来
阐释此问题(关于假定getView调用的顺序)的所在
and actually a great example of making assumptions about the ordering of getView calls
这个例子是最近发生在我们Android团队内部的一件事
is something that happen to us inside the Android team really recently
开发Gmail程序时就犯了假定getView调用顺序的错误
the Gmail application was making one of these assumptions
在Froyo系统中,开发人员对UI做了一些改变
and so in Froyo,they (changes) something about their UI
这些改变在ListView中走了一条不同的代码路径
that made them go through different (code) path in ListView
这把getView的调用顺序给改变了
and suddenly the order of getView calls changed
这导致在你收件箱中的每一封邮件
and every single one of your emails in your inbox
看起来都跟第一封邮件一样
looked like the first email in your inbox
这里的bug不是出在ListView身上,而是出在应用程序身上
and that wasn't (a bug) in ListView,that was a problem in the application
因此它假定了它会
cause they were assuming that they would
按顺序得到0,1,2,3位置上的视图
give you 0,give you 1,give you 2,give 3
然而事实并不如此
which wasn't the case any more
为了进一步掌握,想一下我们有
to give an idea,think we have
至少有4到5种不同的方式来
在ListView中来进行对视图的布局
at least 4,5 different ways to perform layout in ListView
有时,我们会从屏幕底部开始来进行布局
sometimes we are gonna start by doing the layout from the bottom of the screen
有时我们会从顶部,还有时我们会从中间
sometimes we start from the top,sometimes we start from the middle
因此,不要对这些函数的调用想当然
so again,don't make any assumption about the other of the calls
好的
ok
当你数据源变化时,你该怎么办
so what happens when your data changes
无论何时当你数据源变化时,你都需要更新你的适配器
whenever your data changes you need to update your adapter in some way
你还需要告诉ListView,
and not only that,but you need to tell ListView
你的适配器的确是更新了
that the adapter was updated
你通过调用notifyDatasetChanged来做到这点
you do this by calling notifyDatasetChanged
这个方法的作用是触发你的ListView重新扫描你的适配器
this basically triggers ListView to rescan your adapter
对其显示在屏幕上的数据项视图
for the views that are on screen
重新填充数据
repopulate them
还干各种细活,比方说还能自动滚动列表
deal with any sort of manipulations in terms of scrolling a list
当现在的数据元素减少时
if there is few data elements in there now
或者当数据元素增多时
or growing a lot,there is more
如果你的数据数据集变得不可用时
if your dataset becomes unavailable for example
比方说你的数据存储文件不在了
if,like your backing file gets deleted
或者你的网络连接中断了
if your network access goes out
调用这个notifyDatasetInvalided会通知我们
notifyDatasetInvalided() will tell us
ListView中已经没有数据了,数据全部没了
that there is no more data,it's entirely gone
这样我们就不会再去尝试获取数据了
and we are not going to trying access it anymore
这点我们之后还会谈到,但是
and we'll talk about it more or later,but
notifyDatasetChanged被及时调用是非常重要的
it's very very important to call notifyDatasetChanged()
大多数我所看到的跟ListView有关的bug
most of the bugs i (see filed) against  ListView
都是由于程序没有正确调用
notifyDatasetChanged而产生的
usually come from the application not calling notifyDatasetChanged correctly
这个方法一定要在UI线程被调用
it has to be called on the UI thread
以及每次当你修改你的适配器时,都要被调用一次
and it has to be called every time you modify your adapter
尤其是当你把适配器中数据项的个数更改时
especially when you change the number of items inside the adapter
我不记得具体是哪个发布版本了,Donut或者Eclair,
那就是1.6或者2.0
and that's really...i don't remember for what release,it was may be Donut or Eclair,so 1.6 or 2.0
我们在ListView中加入了一个新的异常
we added a new exception in ListView
这个异常尝试去侦测
so it tries to detect the case
当你改变了适配器的内容而没有通知ListView时
when you change the adapter without telling the ListView
如果侦测到了,那么程序就会崩溃
when that happens now we crashed
我们会抛出一个异常,会在Logcat中显示很长很长的信息
we throw an exception and we have very very long and detail message in the logcat
来告诉你在所处的线程中做了一些很糟糕的事情
telling you that you are doing something wrong probably with the thread
这个异常信息有助于你改正程序
so if you see that message,pay attention to it,it's very important that you fix this issue
之前我们提到过,ListView可以对不同的视图类型进行处理
so we mention before that ListView handle different view types for you
大多数情况下你像展示不止一种数据类型在ListView中
a lot times you have more than one type of data that you wanna display it at once
某些列表元素可能包含有图片
certain list elements you may wanna include Images in
而有些你想加入引用文本
certain ones may have extended (quote) text
这些不同类型的数据最终要展示到同一个列表中
all of these things end up being different types of data that you wanna display within the same list
ListView可以帮助你做到这点
and ListView will help you out with this
适配器中有个方法叫getItemViewType
the function getItemViewType on your adapter
此方法会告诉ListView
tells ListView what type
在此位置的视图的类型是什么
the view at that position should be
因此
so
这里返回值仅仅是一个整数值而已
generally this is just an integer parameter that you pass back
那么
so
你有多少种类型
however many types you have
那么getViewTypeCount中就是返回多少
return that from getViewTypeCount
ListView会维护
and ListView will maintain
从根本上来说,会对每种视图类型维护一个回收器
basically a recycler for each one of these different view types that you have
当getView被调用的时候,ListView总会
传给你正确类型的convertView
and it'll always be ready to hand you back the correct one when getView gets called
还有一点关于数据项类型也是很重要的
and something also very important about the item types
那就是当你实现getViewTypeCount的时候,
所返回的类型个数
that the number of types you have,so when you implement the getViewTypeCount()
必须是一个常数值,在整个过程中,此值不能被改变
that number has to be constant through out the duration
在适配器的整个生命周期过程中
through out the lifecycle of your adapter
你都不能让这个数字发生改变
you can not make the number change
你这样做是可以的,你可以声明10种数据类型,
但是实际上你只用了2种
it's ok if you said that you have ten types and you actually end up using only two
这样做并不会产生资源的浪费
it's not gonna waste in your resources
但是如果你改变了这个值,那么ListView中会发生很糟的事情
but if you change that number,then very very bad things will happen in ListView
你会看到很古怪的列表展示效果
and you will see like very weird behavior
that might be (vary source) from time to time
因此
so
尝试找出你最终要用到的类型数量
try to figure out what is the maximum number of types we gonna need
然后在getViewTypeCount中返回
and return that number from the getViewTypeCount()
当你读取数据源变得很慢的时候发生了什么
so what happens when you have data source that's really slow
可能你正在从网络中获取数据
you are bringing something in over network
或者你正在读取一个很大的文件
you're reading a large file
换一种说法,你的UI线程不能够及时响应了
one way another you are not going to be able to keep up with that on your thread and still remain responsive
那么
so
取数据这个操作可以发生在任何地方,
你可以另开一个线程专门来取数据
fetching that data can actually happen in anywhere,you can spend on another thread
在这个线程里对网络发送请求来取数据
send over request out to the network
这都是可以的
it doesn't matter
但是很重要的一点要牢记
but the important thing to remember is that
提交适配器变化的操作一定要在UI线程
you always commit your adapter changes on the UI thread
再一次善意提醒,一定要及时调用notifyDatasetChanged
and once again,make sure you call notifyDatasetChanged
牢记
so
任何数据的改变都要在
any changes have to be reflected
UI线程上反映出来
on that UI thread
你还必须保证调用notifyDatasetChanged的地方
and you also have to call notifyDatasetChanged in the same UI event
与你提交变化给适配器的地方处在相同的UI事件中
where you commit the changes to the adapter
你不能改变了适配器的内容之后,
you can't change the adapter then sometimes either
再把notifyDatasetChanged发送给ListView
send notifyDatasetChanged to the ListView
因为这两个操作不在同一时候,
那么在这两个操作之间也许会有一个对布局的请求
cause in between that may be a request for a layout
这样当notifyDatasetChange发生时,
ListView会有互斥的数据
and then ListView will have conflicting data
接下来我们会将一些数据项属性的内容
then we are gonna talk about a couple of item properties
第一个要讲的内容很简单
so the first one is actually really simple
那就是失效数据项
it's the ability to disable these items
如果你看过Adapter的源码的话,
你就知道当你创建自己的Adapter时
if you look at the adapter interface so when you create your own adapter
会有一个方法来通知ListView每条数据项是否是可用的
there is a method that you tell ListView weather or not a item is enabled
默认的实现是所有的Item都是可用的
by default,all items are enabled
一个可用的数据项可以让你设置selector
and having an enabled item lets you (selected) with the drawables
所以你会在默认的主题中看到
so which you gets with the default theme
每个item背后的橘黄色强调
the orange highlights behind the item
同时,可用的item还是可点击的
it lets you also click the item
当你点击的时候,你会获取到onListItemClick的事件
and you can get an onListItemClick event
但是在某些情况下
in some cases though
你想让某些item失效(不可用)
you want to disable those items
失效数据项并不一定是向用户展示此item不可用,例如:
and disabling items is not necessarily to show the user that this item is not available for instance
其还可以用来表示此item请求的web服务器暂时不可用
it may be a web server that's not reachable
同时,失效的item还可以用来简单的
创建一种不同数据项类型
it's also for simply to create different items
不同的类型意味着不同的视觉展示
items have different visual appearance
这儿有一个例子,这个例子是我们的应用市场app
so there's an example,this is market application
如果你注意到了其中的绿色的标题项时
if you look at the green headers in the middle of the ListView
这些数据项就是无效的数据项
those are disabled items
是这些item失效的原因是其只用起到头标的作用即可
(用于指示出列表中不同的分段)
so the items are disabled because they serve as header so they just indicate different sections of the list
很显然,这个item不需要被轨迹球选择或者被点击
and obviously,it wouldn't make sense to able to select them with trackball or to click on them
所以说,这是一个很有用的特性
so it's a very simple feature that
被深度的用于android平台
use heavily inside the Android platform
因此,你可以选择将这点特性集成到你的应用中去
and you can agree choose of it inside your own applications
有时,在列表中仅仅获取到一个点击的事件是不够的
so sometimes you just getting a click event on the specific list item isn't enough
你想让用户在列表中做出多选或者单选
you want the user the be able to make choices within that list
你可能想让这个选择性变得互相独立
you may want that choice to be mutually exclusive
这次你就可能每次只能选择一个数据项,
你可能也想让用户做出多选
you can only select one item at a time,you may want the user to be able to select multiple items out of the specific list
基于以上原因,我们提供了ListView的选择模式
so for that,we provide choice mode
single choice模式赋予每个item单选性
you have a single choice mode which gives you radio button and once again
用于互相独立的选择
for mutually exclusive choices
你还有multiple choice mode
you have multiple choice mode
利用这点,你可以对列表中的数据项进行多选
which lets you check a number of items within the list
那么你要用什么方法来获取到选取的结果呢
so what happens when you want to get that check state back out and
从而,读出这些状态来设置视图(radio or checkbox)
read it in another part of your application
这里有一些方法是你可以调用的
you can call several methods on ListView
getCheckedItemPosition此方法
会在单选模式下返回选中的item的位置
getCheckedItemPosition will return the position of the items you've selected in single choice mode
getCheckedItemPositions在多选模式下管用
if you are multiple choice mode,you can call getCheckedItemPositions plural
这个方法会返回你选中的所有item的位置
and that will give you all the positions that are currently checked
我们之前提到过,有个固定id的概念在适配器中
but we mention before there is this concept of stable id within the adapter
此概念表示在适配器中的每一项都有
where each value within the adapter has
一个整数值来表示其唯一性
an integer that specifies uniquely that value
无论适配器中执行了删除操作或者插入操作,
其值都能保持不变
no matter how the position may change due to other deletions and insertions
因此
so
如果你想对你的适配器做很多插入或删除操作时
if you are going to have a lot of deletions and insertions within your adapter over time
还有你要对适配器进行多选
and you are also making choices
getCheckedItemIds这个方法就会返回被选中的item的id
then you can use getCheckedItemIds to refer to those items by id
这样就克服了position不能跟数据集平行的缺陷
so that the positions don't get out of alignment with your actual data
怎么回事儿...
come on
好了,继续...
there we go
这里看到的是两种选择模式的例子
so here is an example of each one in the choice modes
你可能在铃声选择器中已经见到过了
you've probably seen this before in the ringtones selector
另外一个是Gmail中的lable选择器
and in the selector for which labels you wanna display in gmail
这些看起来都不咋地,
so this all looks by default,but
但是你写的时候,你可以在getView方法中
全权控制视图如何显示
as always,you are gonna control the presentation through getView
你可以发挥自己的想象,使其看起来充满妙趣
so you can make these look as fancy as you like
这件关于ListView的事情很让人摸不着头脑
now,something is very (...) by ListView is
那就是我们如何处理可聚焦的数据项
how we handle focusable items
我们UI工具团队中遇到的最大限制之一就是
one of the big constraints that we have on the UI toolkit team is
注:轨迹球(带键盘的手机中,上下左右+确认键),
现在已经不怎么用了
我们一方面要支持轨迹球,另一方面还要支持触摸屏
that we need to support trackballs and touch screens
起初我们的方案是,一旦你触摸了屏幕
and we decide in the early (on) that as soon as you touch the screen
所有的聚焦选择都失效
the focus all the selection goes away
这就是我们提供选择模式的原因
and that's why we have the choice mode for instance
你不能想着用户点击了某项item,
其被选中的状态就会一直保存在列表中
you can't just let the user tap an item in the list and keep the selection on screen
ListView会很为难,哥,我真的做不到啊
ListView like,"we will fight really hard to make that not happen"
那么
so
我们默认所作的是
something we've done is that by default
如果你把某种可聚焦的控件放进了ListView
if you put a focusable item inside the ListView item,for instance
例如,你的列表中的某项有一行按钮
if you have a row in your list contains a couple of buttons
默认的实现是,当你使用轨迹球时,
整行将会作为一个整体被选中
by default,the entire row will be selected when you use the trackball
这里的原因是,
and the reason for that is that it will be very awkward
如果我们把触摸球的选择分发给
to have trackball navigation that we go from selecting the whole item
此行中的子控件时,这会显得很笨拙
to selecting new items inside the row itself
难么,聪明的你如果先改变这点的话
so if you want more control over that
如果你想让轨迹球往行里面移动
if you want to have selectable,focusable items inside the row
你可以对ListView倾诉你的需求
you can tell ListView that you want that to happen
setItemsCanFocus传入true
so if you call setItemsCanFocus and you pass true
就代表你对ListView说,我想选行里的子控件
you are telling ListView,"ok,so none my rows,i don't want to select the entire rows,i want to select stuff inside the rows"
这里的例子展示了这种用法,在左边,是我们的联系人程序
and we have an example here,so on the left side,we have the contact application
在列表的数据项中,头像是可聚焦的(ImageButton)
you can see that there is focusable item on the left
当你点击时,就会快速显示联系人
that's the quick contact action
但是默认的实现是,用轨迹球是选不到这里的
but by the default,they decided they didn't want the user to be able to select that with trackball
因此当你使用轨迹球时,你只能选择整个行
so when you use the trackball you can only select the entire row,the entire contact
另一方面,在Twitter的应用中
on the other hand,in the Twitter application
他可以让你用轨迹球选择每个推文中的链接
they use that feature to be able to lets you select the links inside each tweet
因此,你不能选中整个推文
so you won't be able to select the entire tweet
但是你可以在链接之间进行导航
but you can navigate with the trackball from link to link
那么
so
我们意识到这样实现是笨拙的,有时会很无奈
we realize that it would be awkward and sometimes is difficult
当你有很复杂的列表项时,其中可能有好几处触摸区域
when you want to have complex list items that have several touchable areas
虽然有方法能够克服困难
there are various to handle that
这些方法在邮件列表中,或者论坛中都能找到
they are like (good) tutorials and explanations on various (mail list since) forum on the web
但是这点上我们显然做得不够,在未来我们会加以改善
and this is something we'd like to improve in the future
如果你有好点子来指导我们如何做的话
so if you have idea on how we should do that
尽情与我们交流在Android群组中
feel free to contact us (via) android groups,we can talk about it
我的一个想法是,搞一个ListView2号出来,
使其只支持触摸模式
my current idea is to may be have a ListView2 that will support only touch mode
那么这样的话,应用的表现就会跟其他平台相差无几了
and it will be closer to what you see on other platforms
当你显示列表时,如果不给一个情景引导的话,
会让人感到很奇怪
so it's pretty weird you have a list that you just wanna show without a context
通常,你要让用户知道,这个列表中有什么,
以及用户如何操作此列表
generally,you wanna say something to the user about what this list contains and what they are supposed to do with it
那么,为了这个需求
so,for this
我们回头再看看最近发布的Twitter应用
again,we come back to the Twitter application that was recently released
这里如你所见的
as you can see here
我们有几个数据项来提供上下文
we've got several different items that provider context
来让用户知道他在看什么,应用中顶部有一个头部
for what is you are looking at,we have the tweets header up top
这里告诉用户,我们正在看GoogleIO的推文话题
we say that we were looking at tweets by Google IO in this case
除此之外,在底部,我们又加了一个额外的数据项
but also at the bottom,we have this extra element
详细说明我们现在处于列表的底部,
列表在等待命令加载新的内容
that specifies that we were at the end of the list,and we were loading new content on demand
这就是一个很好的例子,来运用头部和底部在ListView中
so this is an example of several different ways of handling headers and footers within ListView
如果你想有一个固定的头部
if you wanna use a fixed header
well
这很简单,你要做的就是
this is pretty easy,all you need to do is
在ListView的上面或者下面布局一个新的视图就行
place other views either above or below your ListView
这样的布局你可能见到过
and you probably seeing layouts quiet a bit like this before
但是如果你想让上面的头部也能滚动的话,
事情就变得有点复杂了
if you want them to scroll,then things get a little bit more complex
但是
but
我们为你做了一点工作,
以至于你不用太多担心其如何实现
we've done a little bit the work for you,so that you don't have to worry to much about it
addHeaderView和addFooterView
addHeaderView and addFooterView
这两个方法,其用法都是你先规定好一个视图,
both you specify a view that will appear at the very beginning and very end
出现在适配器中其他列表项的顶部或者底部
of all the other list content in your adapter
你可以传入任何你想要的视图
you can put whatever you want in here
需要注意的是,这两个方法要在setAdapter之前被调用
however,the trick to this is that you have to call these functions before setAdapter()
由此,你可以猜猜其内部的实现原理
and that might give you a little bit of clues how this implement under the hood
这两个方法也可以传入第二个参数isSelectable
both of these functions also take an extra parameter is selectable
这会告知最终的适配器
this corresponds to wether or not the final adapter being used
这两个加入的数据项是否是可用的
will report back to the list these items are enabled
这里的命名有点问题
there is a little bit naming conflict about that
我们很惭愧,这种做法可不是那么直观
sorry about it,it's not the most intuitive thing in the world
那我接着说了
so
也许你已经猜到了,ListView添加头部或者底部的实现
是在内部把适配包裹到里另一个适配器中去了
as you might have guessed,ListView does this by internally wrapping your adapter inside another one
它把第一个和最后一个数据项的数据类型做了改变
and it will turns different view types for the first and last item
这里你要小心的是
so what you need to be careful of with this
当你调用getAdapter的时候,你不能假设
is that you don't make assumptions that if you do getAdapter on your list
列表所返回的适配器就是你setAdapter时的适配器
这里已经不是同一个适配器了
that is going to be the same object instance you passed in to setAdapter in the first place
让我们快速的看看列表的选择器吧
and we gonna take look at the list selectors very quick
当你使用轨迹球在列表中导航时,
你所看到的就是列表选择器
so the list selectors is what you see when you use the track ball to navigate around
这也是当你在某个数据项上进行长按时,你所见到的
it's also what you see when you perform a long list on the item
或者当你轻触数据项时
or you simply tap the item,when you tap an item,you can
你会看到选择器在屏幕显示150毫秒左右
you will see the selector appear on screen briefly for a like 150 millisecond or something like that
你可以自定义列表选择器
you can customize the list selector
但是你要意识到的是
but what's really important to realize is that
首先,列表选择器在触摸模式下是不显示的
first of all,the list selector is not showing in the touch mode
因此,如果你用轨迹球选择了某个数据项,
之后你又触摸了屏幕
so if you select an item with a trackball then you touch the screen like where i mention before
选择器的状态就会消失
the selection disappears
其次,选择器默认情况下是在数据项的底部的
and also the selector by default is shown behind the items
因此,当你的数据项有自定义背景时,
选择器的显示就会出问题
so this can be a problem if your item has custom backgrounds
因此.如果你的数据项的背景纹理或者颜色的话
so if you have texture or custom color
不好意思
sorry
或者自定义的颜色的话
or custom color
你就不能看到你的选择器了
that you won't see...you won't be able to see a selector
在ListView中,不论是在XML中还是JAVA API中
so on the ListView in XML does also equivalent in the Java API
你可以对drawSelectorOnTop传入true
you can use the attribute called drawSelectorOnTop and if you specify it true
这样我们就会把选择器显示在视图上面
then we gonna put the selector on top
不过如果你对默认的选择器这么做的话,
你就不能看到你的数据项了
if you do that with the default selector,then you won't be able to see your item
因为我们的默认选择器还是在item的后面("不解...")
because our default selector is still on your back
这样做没啥效果
and it won't work really well
这里,我们展示的是市场上的一款叫做多彩笔记的应用
so here,we have an example of an application on market called color notes
这里的数据项都有自定义的背景
as you can see,their items have a custom background color
这里的背景色是黄色
so the items have yellow background
这个应用为数据项创建了自己的选择器
and they've created their own selectors
他们创建了一个简单的橘黄色的边框
so they've created a simple orange border and
他们是怎么做到的呢,很简单,
就是设置drawSelectorOnTop为true
how they've done that was simply to set drawSelectorOnTop equals true attribute on ListView
这样我们就把选择器放在了数据项的上面了
so that we move the selector back on top of the item
现在,如果你想有一个这样的选择器
now,if you wanna it to have a selector there was a (fields)
在这里,你看到的是一个空心的
cause you can see here,that is hollow
如果你还想要这种橘黄色的高亮
so if you still want the orange highlights
除此之外,你还想要一个自定义的背景色
but you also want it the a custom background color
你就需要多做一点点的工作了,
在接下来的几个PPT中,你会知道如何去做
you need to do a little more working,we will see how to do that in a couple of slides
这是一种XML,你用来创建自己的选择器
this is the kind of XML that you have to write to create a list selector
请问,有多少人曾经创建过自定义的选择器
so how many of you have ever create you own custom selector
有一些
quiet a few
我确定刚开始的时候,你会很困惑,如何让其起效果
and i'm sure that you'll beat puzzle (at first on) how to make it work
从根本上来讲,你创建了一个drawable,来告诉framework
basically,the idea is that you create a drawable that will tell the framework
根据当前数据项的状态来决定用哪个drawable
what drawable to use based on the current state of the item
因此我们有很多不同的状态,我们有窗口是否在聚焦
so we have a bunch of different states,we have whether or not the window is focused
控件是否在被聚焦
whether or not the widgets is focused
控件是否被按下或者选中
whether or not the widgets is pressed or selected (eta.)
正如这里你所见的
as you can see here,usually
通常你要非常准确的描述这些状态
you have to be extremely precise about the states
请看第六行的代码
so if you look at line number 6
这里如果item是被聚焦的
we were saying,"ok,if the item is focused
以及它不是无效的,以及它是被点击的
and,it's not enabled and it's pressed
这时,我们才会采用list_selector_background_disabled
then we'll gonna use the drawable in the list_selector_background_disabled"
最好的做法不是从头再写
so the best you can do is not to write those from scratch
而是从android平台的源码中引用
just grab the source code of the Android platform
我没记错的话,ApiDemos里面有不少例子
or i think we have some examples in the ApiDemos
你只需要把我们定义好的状态拿来用,
然后定义自己的drawable就行
and just (keep in) base what we have and just replace everything with your own drawables
这里也有一个小小的技巧
there is also one little trick here
请看代码13行
if you look at them line number 13 for instance
我们引用了list_selector_background_transition
we are referring a drawable called list_selector_background_transition
这里的drawable是当你长按列表中的表项时进行动画的
that's the drawable that animates when you long click an item in a list
这里的动画是从橘黄色变为白色
it turns from orange to white
如果你对此效果的实现感兴趣
if you're interested in how to make that happen
你可以去查看我们的源码
you can just go check out our source code
你会看到我们XML中的动画是如何定义的,
实际上这很简单
and you will see how to declare that kind of animation in XML,it's actually pretty simple
如果在你的列表中的表项有自定义的背景
now,if your items in the list have custom background
自定义的不透明的背景,就像刚刚我们看到过的应用截屏
custom opaque background like we just saw on the screenshot
但是你仍然想要一个不透明的选择器背景在表项的下面
and you still want to have an opaque selector background behind the item
这有一个妙计你可以拿去用
there is a very simple tricky you can use
你可以用一个选择器的drawable作为你的背景
you can use a selector drawable for your items background
你要做的全部事情就是当其被选中时,
将其背景设为透明
and all you have to do is give it transparent background when it selected
你可以看看这里的代码,仅仅几行的xml
so here you can see,it's only a few lines of XML
当被选中的时候,
and you can see that for the state_selected equals (for the selected states)
其背景为透明色
with the transparent color
0来表示透明色
which is the just a number 0
其他情况下,我们就用任意颜色来表示我们的背景了
and in every other case,we just use whatever color we decide to use for our item
这是个小小的技巧,但是能让你
以一种全新的方式自定义ListView
so this is a very simple,but it lets you customize your ListView in a whole new ways
接下来谈谈ListView中的一些其他特性
so coming into a few the other features of ListView
对ListView已经很熟悉的各位
as any of you who have worked with ListView so far will probably already know
相信你们对这个话题的内容已经了然于胸了
there is whole other (grab bag) functionality that's available for you to use
因此,我们会精选一些快速的讲
so we were gonna go though a couple of those really quickly
首先
so
transcript模式
transcriptMode
有多少人尝试过去写聊天客户端呢
how many have you tried to write anything with assembly some sort of chat client
有人么
anyone
不错,我们有这样的人才
ok,we have a few
我希望你会发现transcriptMode的好用之处
so,hopefully,you found transcriptMode useful
这个模式会根据内容的变化来改变列表的行为
so this changes the behavior of the list when the content changes
当你调用notifyDatasetChanged时
so when you call notifyDatasetChanged
你的列表会执行另一种布局更新的路线
your list performs another layout path
这个模式定义了当新内容到来时,
ListView进行滚动的方向
this defines where we were going to scroll to,now that you have your new content
如果这个属性是不可用的话,这也是我们的默认设置
if it is disabled which is our default
当你的适配器内容改变时,我们不会自动滚动任何内容
then we don't scroll when anything changes in terms of your adapter contents
如果你把它设置成正常的话,那么
if you set transcriptMode to normal,however
当你在列表的尾部添加内容时
then if you add the edge of the list
新内容来会传递到列表中
and new content comes in
我们就会把列表向下滚,如果最后一个数据项是可见的话
then we gonna go ahead and scroll to the bottom if the last item is visible
因此
so
这基本上是
this basically makes such that
如果你现在在聊天客户端的列表中部时,
你滚动列表去查看历史消息时
if you are in the middle of chat client,and you scrolling back in history
此时,又有新消息到来的话
and a new message comes in
此时你不能马上将视图滚动到最底部
you're not gonna scroll the bottom immediately there
但是如果你此时就在底部
but if you already at the bottom
你的注意力有点集中来消息到来时
and sort of paying attention to (live stream) things coming in
这里我们就会自动将列表滚动,使最后一个数据项可见
then we are gonna go ahead scroll down and make that last item visible for you
如果你在做一个聊天客户端,通常
so if you are doing a chat client,usually you're also
你不想要任何东西都从上往下堆砌
you don't wanna everything just (stack) in from the top
这并不是聊天客户端的标准
that's not usually the way that you view a chat client
因此我们有stackFromBottom这个属性,
可以使所有的元素
so we have stackFromBottom that makes all the elements
从下往上堆砌
as described
从下往上堆砌根据聊天的历史记录
stack up from the bottom in terms of like a chat history
一条一条的往上堆砌,你发一条消息,
我们就在底部堆砌一个表项
is sort of match up with any sort of input (field) you may have below it
因此我们把列表项以逆序堆砌了
so we stack items in reverse order
我们堆砌的第一条(最底部的一条)
就是你发送的最后一条消息
and we start with the last item from the adapter
因此,你的适配器中的顺序还是不变的
so your oder still stays the same
我们只是逆序遍历表项进行显示而已
but we just sort of traverse differently,once again
但是你不能也假设getView的调用也是逆序的
this comes down to don't make assumptions about the order of call to getView()
所以嘛
so
这对任何聊天客户端的创建都是很有用处的
again this is really useful for any sort of check client that you might be trying to create
这里有个例子,你可能之前也见到过
here is an example of it,you probably seeing something very similar before
这里用到了transcriptMode
this is using both transcriptMode
和stackFromBottom.正如你所见到的,我们是从底部
and stackFromBottom.as you can see we were building a list
开始构建这个列表的,这样以来
我们的空白空间就留在顶部而不是底部了
from the bottom so we have the empty space from the top rather than down below
每一个列表都支持一种特性叫做文本过滤
every list supports a feature called textFiltering
这个特性是超级有用的,在我们的第一台设备上
this is the feature that always extremely useful on the first device
第一台android设备,那就是T-mobile的G1了
on the first Android device that come out the T-mobile G1
因为它带有一个键盘,如果你了解这个特性的话,
你会非常频繁的使用到它
because it had a keyboard,and (if you have a draw) it you can actually use that feature pretty easily
在其他的设备中,你需要自己准备好键盘
on other devices,you have to bring this stuff keyboard
按着menu键,才能用上这个功能
by keeping the menu key pressed to be able to use it
那么这个特性能让你干什么呢
so what it does is it lets you
这里有个截屏,例如,在音乐程序中
here is the screenshot,so for instance,as a music application
你把键盘连接上之后
you should bring up the keyboard
当你敲击字母的时候
and you start typing
列表就会根据你输入的内容来过滤列表内容
you are gonna filter the content via list
因此,我们这里会只显示以你输入字母为子集的列表项
so we gonna show you only the items that match whatever you type
这里的匹配规则全部取决于你的适配器的实现
and the matching rules depend entirely on your adapter
我们有一些适配器默认实现了一些过滤器
we have some adapters that by default,implements a filter
例如,CursorAdapter和ArrayAdapter
for instance,CursorAdapter and the ArrayAdapter
都有一个对过滤器的基本实现
have basic implementation of the filter
我记得在ArrayAdapter中,我们只做了是否相等的比较
i think in ArrayAdapter we just do (an equality) comparisons
如果你输入的内容被包含在表项的内部
so if whatever you type equals what the item contains
我们就会显示此列表项,否则就会将其移除列表
then we gonna show( it,others will be) removed from the list
如果你自定义视图的话,来实现
自己的过滤器的话是很容易的
it's very simple to implement yourself if you have a custom adapter
你要做的就是实现Filterable接口
all you have to do is implement the Filterable interface
然后在getFilter方法中创建好过滤器
and then implement the getFilter method
在getFilter的方法中,你要返回一个新的过滤器的实例
the getFilter(),you have to return a new instance of the Filter class
而过滤器类仅仅只有两个方法
and the Filter class has only two methods
在android中,过滤器机制的好处在于
what's nice about the filtering mechanism in Android is that
我们为你干了大多数的困难工作,
我们在背后的线程中处理所有事情
we do all the hard work for you,so we handle everything on the background thread
当用户开始打字的时候
so we gonna invoke when user start typing
我们将调用performFiltering在背后的线程中
we gonna invoke this method called performFiltering on the background thread
你可以在这个方法里面做任何事情,
任何开销的事情都行
so you can do whatever you want in here,it can be very expensive,doesn't matter
因为这并不会让UI线程受阻
cause you're not going to block the UI
当用户开始输入的时候,我们会传递给你一个字符串
so we gonna pass you as a CharSequence whatever the user has typed
你可以根据用户输入的内容来
来重建一个数据集用于ListView的显示
and then it's up to you to rebuild a list of data that you want to display in the ListView
为了将选出来的数据进行显示
to display that new set of data
你必须返回一个FilterResults的集合
you have to return a set of FilterResults
FilterResults是一个简单的类
the FilterResults is a simple class
其中包含了在过滤之后你想先要显示的表项
that contains a number of items that you want to show after filtering
这是一个Object,这个Object任何你想要的
and ...an Object,so the Object is whatever you want
它可以是一个游标,也可以是一个数组,等等
it's only used to be able...it can be a cursor,it can be an array,it can be whatever you need
之后,当你把FilterResults返回后
so then when you return that FilterResults
我们会在UI线程中调用publishResults
we gonna invoke the publishResults on the UI thread
我们在参数中传回FilterResults对象
and we gonna give you back the FilterResults Object
你的工作仅仅是把放进FilterResults的东西取出来
and your job in this method is simply to extract the data that you put in the FilterResults
对你的adapter进行修改
and communicate to your adapter
这里就是你修改你适配器的时候
so this is where you modify your adapter
这里也是你调用notifyDatasetChanged的地方
it's also where you call notifyDatasetChanged
实现一个过滤器就是这么简单
implementing a filter is pretty simple
他虽然涉及到几种不同的类,
但是如果你深入Android源码的话
it involves a couple of classes,but again,if you look at the Android source code
你深入去看ArrayAdapter或者CursorAdapter的源码时
then you go to the source code,the ArrayAdapter or the CursorAdapter
你会看到我们是怎么做的,那简直弱爆了
you will how we've done it,it's extremely simple
这里有趣的一点是
something that's interesting here
那就是,当结果为空的时候,
你要调用notifyDatasetInvalidate
for instance,if the number of result is zero,you might want to call notifyDatasetInvalidate
来通知ListView没有更多的数据可显示
to tell ListView that there is no more data to display
so
我们接着要讨论使用ListView时会遇到的一些情况
then we gonna...we want to talk about a few issue that's you might encounter with ListView
请问有多少人曾经遇到过,你有一个很漂亮的ListView
how many of you have ever seen that like you have a beautiful ListView
你有一个自定义的背景,但是一旦当你滚动的时候,
列表就全变黑了
you have custom background,and you start scrolling and everything is black
嗯,有一些
ok,so a few already
那么其他人应该没有试着去自定义过ListView的背景了
so the other ones are probably not try to customize background of ListView
这里的原因很简单
the reason for that is simply
在于我们早期对ListView的一项优化
because of optimization that we've done very early in ListView
so
我们对于ListView出现的问题是在针对低端机时,如G1
the problem we have with ListView especially on lower devices like T-mobile G1
或者更低端的设备时
or even slower devices
当你开始滚动大量的数据项时,特别是在飞划的时候
is that when you scroll through a lot of items especially when you are flinging
你会看到每秒都有一打一打的表项在滚动
and you see that dozens and dozens of items go by every second
这样我们就会在屏幕上做很多blending操作
we do a lot of (blending) on screen
blending是一种开销很大的操作
blending is very expensive operation
因为列表的表项默认是透明的
that's because list items by default are transparent
为了避免blend的过多执行,我们
so to avoid that,what we do with that
我们试着搞清楚列表背后的颜色是什么
we trying to figure out what is the color behind the list
默认情况下,我们知道它是黑色的
and by default we know what that color is,it's some kind of black
因此,我们就把每个数据项转化成一个位图
so we turn every item into a bitmap
我们对此位图的背景以列表背后的背景色做填充
we fill that the background of that bitmap with the color that's behind the list
一旦我们这样做了,我们就知道所有表项都是不透明的了
so once we've done that,we know that the entirely is going to be opaque
我们就会对视图后面的窗口进行优化,减少其重绘次数
so we can do optimizations like not draw the window that's behind the list
从而在2D库中避免执行blending的代码路径
and avoid (blending code path) in our 2D library
因为那个代码路径比没有blending的代码路径要慢很多
which happen to be slower than the non blending code path
这种优化发生在
and that truly that optimization happens
每当你的手指触摸到屏幕时,每当你的手指跟屏幕交互时
as soon as you touch the screen,as soon as your finger comes into contact with the screen
这就会使得在屏幕上的所有表项变成位图
which (on)all the items on screen into bitmaps
对这个问题的解决方案是简单的,
只需要设置cacheColorHint
so the solution to that issue is simply to specify the cacheColorHint
这个属性指示ListView的背景颜色
this is an indication for ListView about the background color
因此,如果你对其设置了颜色0,
正如在Solution第一行中所见到的
so if you specify the color 0 like in the first line of the Solution here
你是在告诉ListView,我的背景不是纯色
you are telling ListView,"ok,i don't have (solid) background
我的背景可能是纹理,或者是一个很复杂的背景
i may have a texture or have a complex background like
请不要帮我过多的优化
please don't do any optimization"
这里我们就会执行慢一点的代码路径,
我们就能够看到ListView的所有内容了
so then we were gonna to go through a slower code path,but that ListView will be able to see everything
如果你还记得我向你展示的第一张幻灯片的话,
里面我写的那个App有一个木头纹理
and if you remember one of the first slides when i showed you this app i wrote that has a wooden texture
我就这样做了,我让colorHint失效了
this is what i've done,i disable the cacheColorHint
如果你的背景是一种纯色的话
now,if you have a background color,a solid background color
你知道你将要用到的颜色值,
比方说你写的App需要一个绿色的背景
and you know,what is the background color for instance,so writing an application that's green in the background
你可以将这个颜色值赋给colorHint
you can simply specify that color
这样,你不但会得到优化,而且还能得到正确的结果
and then you will get the optimization of ListView and you are gonna the correct result
有多少人在之前来回滚动列表时
so how many of you have been fling through a list before
看到过滚动条根据屏幕的滚动而改变其大小
and seen that the scrollbar along the side of the screen change its size
呦,不少人看到过
yes,ok
我们还把这个叫做蛇
a bunch of you / this (??) equal the snake
是的,这叫蛇效应
right,the snake effect
那我来谈谈吧
so
这个效应的原因是
the reason why this happens is again
我们只画了我们在屏幕上所需要的视图
because we were only drawing as many views as we need on screen
当视图们有着很不一样的视图高度时
and when views have vastly different heights
测量出整个列表的高度,以至于我们可以
being able to measure that,such that we can estimate
估计出还有多少空间剩余来对滚动剩余适配器中的内容
how much more space is left to scroll through across the rest of the adapter
变成了一个很困难的问题
becomes a really difficult problem
我们不得不快速的得出一个大约值
it's the sort thing that we have to get some sort approximation fast
这就导致了最终滚动条的大小变化不正常
and that's why you end up seeing the scrollbar changing size
so
如果你对这种效果不满意,
如果这点使你的App很混乱
if you don't like this effect,this is something that really sort of distract from you app
那么你可以在你的列表中把smoothScrollbar设置为false
then you can go ahead and set smoothScrollbar equals false on you list
这会告诉ListView,不要在乎对表项高度的测量开销
what this will do is it tells ListView don't even try to bother measuring heights of items
不要为了减少开销而返回一个对剩余滚动空间的估计值
to give an estimate of how much scroll space is left
而是要根据在屏幕上的表项来精确计算
instead just use your current position in terms of what items are on screen
这点当你有一个小型的数据集时会显得很难受
this will make a little bit chunky if you have a smaller datasets
但是对于很大的数据集的话
but across very large datasets
那就会使得列表中滚动条看起来真的很平滑了
this will really smooth (out) how the list looks in terms of scrollbars
另一种解决方案是,干脆不用滚动条
another solution is also to just remove the scrollbar
好的,到我了,我看到过很多人这么做
ok,so this is something i've seen (way too) many times
每次我看到有人这么做时,我就会在屏幕前抓狂
and every time (i) see it,i start swearing in front of my screen
然后joe就恨我了,因为他坐在我旁边
then (joe hates me ) may be cause he sits next to me
这是当
this is when
你在XML中把ListView的高度设置成wrap_content时
you set the layout height of a view in XML to wrap_content
那么,有人这么做过么
so,have you ever done that
这没关系了,只是举个手嘛
that's ok,won't be (might) that's you like,just raise your hands
好好好
ok
我喜欢看人们承认自己的错误
i like people admit their errors
这里用warp_content的问题在于ListView是列表的抽象
the problem with wrap_content is that ListView is visualize
ListView可以有两个数据项,也可有上百万个数据项
so ListView can have two items,but it can have millions of items
因此,当你为其设置wrap_content时
so when you tell us wrap_content
那是在说,我想让ListView跟它包含的内容一样大
it means,"ok,i want ListView to be as big as its content"
那么我们这边要不要把百万个表项的高度都测量一下
should we go through the million items and measure them
这样做可能不是一个好主意
that would probably not be a very good idea
但是因为很多人有个需求,或者很多人尝试去那么做
and because so many people are requesting that (or are) trying to do it
那么我们是使其起作用呢还是不让它起作用
we made it work without making it work
因此,如果你把ListView的高度设置成wrap_content的话
so if you set the height of your ListView to wrap_content
我们会测量出你的列表中前三个表项
we gonna measure the first 3 items of your list
这导致很多人对这种行为感到困惑
and actually a lot of people are confused by the behavior
因为有时我在群组上会看到一些消息
because something times i see message on our groups
当我把log语句放到getView方法中时
saying,"hi,when i put (log) statements in the getView method
我会看到ListView请求表项0,1,2然后0,1,2,3,4,5等等
i see that ListView is requesting items number 0,1,2 and then 0,1,2,3,4,5 again
它们不懂这是什么原因,那么原因就是我刚刚说的
and don't get...they don't (why)..that's the reason
因为
because
在布局的过程中,我们会要求适配器前三个表项
during the layout,we were gonna ask the adapter for the first three items
我们会测量它们,然后把它们放进回收器
we gonna measure them,put them in the recycler
然后,我们才会进入调用真实表项的过程
then we will (we need the real items)we are gonna ask these items again
这种做法也是花销很大的
it is expensive
尤其是,如果你在列表中有很复杂的表项时
especially if you have very complex items in you ListView
如果你变态的话,你可以把webView放到你的ListView中
if you are crazy,you put webView inside your list,then
这会导致ListView花费更多时间来侧脸自身
it's gonna take a lot of time for the ListView to measure itself
大说数时间,这并不是你想要的结果
and most of the time,that's really not what you want
因此,你要学着避免这么做
so just avoid it
要么你对ListView的height设置成fill_parent
either you fill_parent as the height of your the ListView
要么如果其在线性布局中时,你可以把其高度设置为0
or if you're in the LinearLayout,you can set the height to 0
然后利用layout_weight来告诉列表共享
and you can use the layout_weight to tell the list to share
布局中剩余的空间
remaining available space
再有就是你可以把你的ListView的高度设置成固定值
and you can also set the height of your ListView to a fixed amounts
比方说200dip,这在G1中就是200像素高
like you can set 200dip (?? to) 200 pixels on the G1
那么,有多少人想这么干过
so how many people have wanted to do this before
在ScrollView中放置一个ListView
a ListView inside of a ScrollView
同志们,举起手来
once again,don't be shy,come on,hands up
ok
so
这样干会出什么事儿呢
what happens here
如果ScrollView会滚动,ListView也会滚动
ScrollView scrolls,ListView scrolls
那么哪一个应该滚动当你手指开始移动的时候
which one should scroll when you start moving
实际上,在这个会谈的之前的周末,我们就被问到过一个问题
we actually get moderator question for this over the weekend for the session already
问我们是否可以对ListView添加一个元素或者一个属性
asking if we could add an element,an attribute rather to ListView to say
用于关闭自己的滚动能力
you know,can i make my ListView scrollable equals false
这样就可以将其放在ScrollView中,
然后让ScrollView来进行滚动了
so that i can put it inside the ScrollView and just let the ScrollView take care of it
快速的答案是这可不成
well,the quick answer to that is nope.
原因是
and the reason for that is that
ListView中可能会有成千山万的表项
once again,a ListView can have tons of thousands possibly even millions of items inside of it
那么
and
正确的答案是,在这种情况下,不可能把这么多的视图
the correct answer in that case is almost never to open up that many views
都打开然后填充到ScrollView中,这样会使得系统
throw them all into a ScrollView and just sort of let the system
死掉,使系统缓慢直至崩溃
die,trying to (chug) long processing all of that
so
通常,这个问题是很多工程师要问的
generally,this is where,you know,any engineer asks the question
好吧,那么你到底想干什么
"ok,what is you're trying to do"
通常,这里的回答是,我想让我的列表中
有一些特别的东西,位于列表之上或者之下
and generally the answer to that is well i wanna have something special either above or below my list
同时我还想只把我的列表内容放到ListView中
but i wanna have mostly just my list content (through) this view
那么
so
如果是那样的话,我们会建议你采用
ListView中头部和尾部的特性
for that,we will really like to point you towards the existing header  and footer features that already exist
如果你有一个布局,你想将其放在列表的上面或者下面
同时还想让真个布局可以滚动
if you have a layout you wanna put above or below a list still have the entire thing scroll
那你就可以把这个列表外的布局设置成头部或者尾部
you can go ahead and set that as a list header or footer
顺便提一下,当我们告诉你
不能把ListView放到ScrollView时
by the way,when we tell you to not put ListView inside of ScrollView
你也不能把ScrollView放到ListView中去
don't put ScrollView inside of ListView.that's equal(??) / yeah  that's true
正如我们在这次会谈开始的时候提到过
yeah,so we mention that before in the talk of the beginning
不过我还想再重复强调一下
but we really want to insist on that point
千万不能尝试着把视图缓存到你的适配器中,
我曾经见过很多人这么干
like do not try to cache views inside your adapter,i've seen that done too (way) too many times
人们这么干的原因有很多
there are various reasons why people try to do it
and
问题在于,这可能起效
the problem is that it might work
大多数情况下,你的列表可以正常工作
most of the time,your list might work
之后,突然间,你的列表中会发生很诡异的事情
and then suddenly some (..?) something really weird is going to start happening
比方说,你可能会失去对表项的点击能力
like may be you won't be able to click the item
还有可能你的表项的动画不工作了
may be you have animation of the item that doesn't work anymore
这里的原因在于,ListView内部有很多种优化
the reason for that is that again,ListView has many optimizations
它有一个很复杂的回收器
it has a very complex recycler
它对屏幕上出现的视图的所有权做了很多的假设
it makes a lot of assumptions about the ownership of the views that on screen
为了让列表滚动的更快,ListView会把
某些视图存到其自身的回收器中
and to make things even faster when ListView puts something in their recycler
那些已经不在屏幕上的视图
that view is not (really) on screen.Like the view
其自身认为自己多少还应该在屏幕上,
但是ListView却不这么认为了
still think that is kind of on screen but the ListView knows that it's not really the case
所以,我们对ListView的优化做了很细很细的工作
so we handle that very very carefully
基于性能的原因
and again for performance reasons
每当你尝试着在你的适配器中尝试对
离开屏幕的其他视图做操作时
and as soon as you try to play tricks in your adapter
你想操作的视图,在我们看来就是僵尸视图了
we were gonna end up with views that are basically zombie views
例如,如果你在getView方法中返回的视图
同样存在于我们的回收器中
for instance,if from the getView return a view that we also have in our recycler
我们就会得到一个本来应该在屏幕上显示视图,
但却不会被显示的视图
we will gonna have a view that's supposed to be on screen,but at the same time that's not on screen
这样干的话,framework之好耸耸肩说,你玩吧
so then the framework just gives us and say,"hi whatever like
我不玩了
i give up"
那么,千万不要假设离开屏幕的视图还能用
so just never ever ever ever ever ever do that
如果你想直接获取某个视图
if you need to access view directly
我们有一个方法叫做getFirstVisiblePosition()
we have a method called getFirstVisiblePosition
这个方法告诉你在你的适配器中,
当前在屏幕上可见的第一个视图的位置
it tells you what is the position in your adapter of the first view that's visible on screen
通过运用这个方法getChildCount
so by using this method and getChildCount
这个方法会告诉你在屏幕上有多少个表项是可见的
that tells you how many items are visible on screen
你可以通过position来获取id
you can easily go back and forth between the index and position
如果基于某些原因,你想要改变
屏幕上某个视图的颜色的话
so if you want to for some reason,like change the color of view on screen
同时,你不想调用notifyDatasetChanged的话
without doing it notifyDatasetChanged
那么你就用getChildAt这个方法来获取到你需要的视图
just use getChildAt of ListView to get the view that's you need
最后
so finally
最后,听了这么多,我认为我们对ListView的使用都清楚了
after all of this,i'm sure that we've sort of hammered home the point
ListView一个很复杂的控件
ListViews are really complex widget
它可能是最复杂的控件在整个android的框架中
it's probably the most complex one we have across the entire Android framework
我们团队花了很多时间在那儿
we spend a lot time in there
不光为了帮助开发者,还为了使其优化程度达到最高
just not only helping developers but just making sure that everything stays working fast optimized
它是为重复的,非绑定的数据进行优化的
and really,it's optimized for repeating unbound data
它对你的应用增加了不少复杂性
it adds a lot complexities to your app
因此,如果你的数据量不多
so if you have a small amount of data
你仅仅只是想要重复的展示相似的表项
that you just wanna have some sort of repeating presentation for
那么你可能不一定非用ListView不可
maybe you don't actually need a ListView for it at all
可能你所要做的仅仅是动态的生成一些视图
maybe all you need in this case is to dynamically generate some views
将其放入到一个垂直方向的线性布局中
put them inside a LinearLayout with a vertical orientation
然后再将这个线性布局放到ScrollView中
and put that layout inside of a ScrollView
这样就会让你的应用变得非常的简单
and this going to make your app a lot simpler
适用于当你的数据集很小时,已经其中有很多特殊项时
if you have a small dataset with a bunch of special cases inside it
这就省去了你大力改造ListView
来满足你的应用需求的功夫
rather than trying to sort of bend ListView into whatever application you have for it
今天我们已经谈了不少内容了
and that's pretty much (we've talked) today
我们还可以继续去讨论ListView的其他特性,
因为ListView中还有许多特性我们没谈到
we could go on for hours about ListView cause there are many features  we haven't talked about
还有很多知识你需要了解
there are many kind of set that you should know about
不过现在,我相信大家都对ListView感到厌烦了
but i'm sure by now,you all pretty bored about ListView
因此,我们要进入问答环节了,如果你要问问题的话,
请到麦克风前
so we gonna start taking questions if you want to ask us questions,you can go to the microphones in the alleys
我们还会抽取一些网上的问题
and we also have questions may be on (moderator)
我们要把这个投影仪放下么
do we want to bring that up?
不要害羞,随便问
don't be shy,you can come ask questions
我们就在这儿.你可以问你想知道的任何问题
we are right here,you can ask us about anything you want
但是只能是关于android
that's really to Android
hi
你刚谈到不能将ListView放到ScrollView中
you said not put ListView in ScrollViews
刚刚的假设是ScrollView是垂直滚动的
but the assumption behind that was the ScrollView be vertically scrolling
如果我们想要模拟Palm的Pre's pager
if we wanna emulate something like the Palm Pre's pager
其中包含着水平的换页和垂直的滚动
where we have vertically scrolling in the horizontal paging
我在论坛上或者其他地方看到有人在尝试
i have seen on forums and stuff,some people trying to do that
这点在Google的运动程序中也做到了
that's also good done with like Google sports application
但是那款我知道的应用,目前并不是开源的
but there's been that particular app as far as i can tell so forth closed source
但是我想要知道怎么做
but we'd like to do know how to do that
基本上,你有一个垂直滚动的ListView,其次
so basically,so you have vertically list scrolling in ListView
你还想要水平的翻页
and you want  to go from page to page horizontally on your right
是,各个ListView中包含相似的不同内容
yeah,many ListViews have similar different content / yeah
你的想法很有趣.你可以用一个水平的ScrollView
so,that is fun.like you can use a horizontal ScrollView
这里重点是,你滚动的两个方向不在同一个坐标轴上
what matters the two scroll that you have are not in the same axes
比方说,我们的home桌面,就有一个分页器,
我们可以在里面放
yeah./ the home screen for instance has a pager,and we could puts
当你打开一个文件的话,这就是一个列表了
when you open the folder on home,it's a list
这里面你可以水平的翻页,也可以滚动列表
and you can still page horizontally and scroll that list
你可以查看启动器的源码
you can look at the source code of the launcher application
这个文件叫workspace.java
it's called workspace.java
我记得我们还有一些其他的应用也有这个特性
and i think we have that in other applications somewhere else
不过,就看workspace.java的源码就行了,
你会发现很容易实现
but,look at the workspace.java in the launcher source code,and you will see it's pretty easy to do
好的/我们有过一些讨论
sure./ and we had a number of discussion about
是否给framework加入一种可以提供水平翻页的控件
specifically adding a widget capable of doing this sort of horizontal paging into the framework
目前我们还没有确定最好的做法
and so far we haven't decide on the best way to do it
目前只是把它放在那儿,以确保人们可以充分利用
just in terms of getting it out here,making sure the people are able to make good use of it
谢谢
thanks
我在我的应用,有一个视图
so,i have a view in may app that is
我这个想法是从Google市场的应用中得到激发的
i tried to have been inspired written from the market (app)
对每个独立的应用,它有一些头部,
还有一些小列表在ListView中
the way the for an individual app,it has some headers and some little list inside lists
我觉得这种效果非常棒
i thought it was really great
我自己实现的过程中
and implementing that myself
我感到很无奈,没有看android源码的情况下
without like looking at how the market source code did was really tricky and
对我而言把线性布局放到
ScrollView中复杂度是似乎有点高啊
it's a little too complicate for me to wanna do the sort LinearLayout in ScrollView
这感觉像是一个ListView
feels like a ListView but
为了做到市场应用的效果
in order to do that,i mean
我最终写了很多的java代码
i end up having to do a lot java of code like
而且不是用一个大的XML文件
instead of one large xml file
而是用很多小的XML文件,
然后在java中将这些文件给绑定在一起
it's a lot of small ones that get bound together through java work
我最终用了一个Merge适配器,这是Mark Murphy做的,
这个适配器帮了我不少忙
i am end up using a merge adapter sort of general thing that (Mark Murphy)made was really helpful for that purpose
我就是觉得用了这么多不同的适配器,这好像有点过头了
it's just (unifying) a lot of different adapters together,it's just feels like overkill
是我没注意到某些东西么.请问你有实现的思路么
is there..am i missing something?and how to do that?
你做的并没有失误.我们几乎也是这么做的
no,that's pretty (much) what we to do it
这里的主要问题是,
ListView被设计为大量数据的列表展示
the big problem again we said ListView was most designed to we have long list of data
每个表项都是一样的
and every item is pretty much the same
我们的确也提供很多不同的表项,正如你刚说的
we do support very different items like you mentioned
但是,当你想要这么做的话,你需要自己干一些事情
but,yeah,when you wanna to do (unfortunately),you have some work to do
是的,那么merge适配器本身是一个非平凡的视图
right.and merge adapter itself is really nontrivial view
它会记录每个表项的位置,并且
in how it has to track what the position number of every item
当我需要的时候,传递给我正确的表项.
这点对我来讲,我是不论如何都不想做的
and show the right i wanted,it just something i would never wanna do myself
但是我猜这情况就是那么个情况
but i guess just the way it is
yeah
ok
如果你有好的建议的话,我确定存在某种解决办法,
但暂时还没有想到
sorry.but again,if you have suggestions like,i am sure there are solutions that we (haven't) thought of like
请与我们联系,或者给我发送bug文件
contact us and we can or (file) bugs
我们真的会去看的
we do look at them
这样我们就知道在未来的发布中做什么了
and we will see what we can do in the future release
我们接下来要看一个线上的问题.
一位来自中国叫Larry的开发者问到
i am gonna take one of the (Google  wave?)questions so someone Larry from China ask us
长按列表项才能获取更多的操作选项
对普通用户来讲是非常古怪的
long click to get more actions for an item is very weird for a normal user
我们是否可以有种跟联系人动作菜单类似的控件
can we have similar UI widget like contacts action menu
就像Twitter自己开发的那样
just like Twitter developed by themselves
那么我觉得他是指在android2.0中当你点击联系人的时
那种弹出式菜单
so i think he is referring to that (little) pop up when you click on the contact in the address book since Android 2.0
我们的答案是,我们有你要的东西
and the answer to that is "yes,sure"
你可以有个这样的控件
you can have one
这里的Twitter会开源
the Twitter app is going to be open source
因此你可以获取到这种控件的源码,
因此你可以用这个控件
so you know,you gonna have the source code for the widget so you'll be able to use it
这其实很简单就能做到
it's actually pretty easy to do
可能这对我来说是如此简单,因为我知道,这是怎么实现的
maybe it's easy for me to say that cause i know,i understand,but
不过一旦你查看了源代码的话,
你就会发现这里面没有太多技术含量
once you see the source code,you will see there is no magic in there
当数据集的长度未知的时候,
有什么建议关于适配器视图呢
yes,thanks.any tips on how to do a adapter view where the length of the dataset is not known
没听懂
pardon me?
数据集的长度未知
the length of the dataset is not known
这其实日历程序的数据集的长度就是未知的
yeah,actually that's where the calendar does
当你在日历中进入议程模式时
the calendar when you...i think when you go into the agenda mode
这里其实它拥有一个无限长的列表
they...basically an infinite list
是通过调用notifyDatasetChanged来改变数据集的
and they do that by just (playing with) notifyDatasetChanged
适配器返回的是
so they just
当前数据集的最大数量
say that they have integer that max value number of items
但是你可以对数据集进行更改
then they just populate (with) more stuff
每次当你调用notifyDatasetChanged时,
你就能更改在适配器中数据集的个数
every time you call notifyDatasetChanged,you can change the number of items in the adapter
因此,你可以在最初的时候返回任意一个数值
so you can just grab a random number
之后,当你意识到你的表项增多时,你可以改变那个数值
and later on,if you realize you have more items you can change that number and keep going
多谢了
thank you
我注意到当我加载位图的时候
i noticed when i used bitmap to loads like (down net) also
整个视图都会被刷新
that the whole views have to be refreshed
有任何像这样的方法吗
is there any method like to say
这样的方法会通知你某个id的视图将会被改变
only one item,an specific item by id is gonna be changed
其实,当你想改变一个列表项的时候,
你可以调用notifyDatasetChanged
actually,so if you are trying to change one item,you call notifyDatasetChanged
尽管整个视图都会被刷新,不过ListView其实很聪明,
应为我们有复杂的回收器
yeah,the whole views is going to be refreshed,but actually ListView is pretty smart here,that's where we have our complex recycler
这个回收器知道视图所刷新的大部分内容
跟刷新前相比是不变的
it's able to figure out that most of what you're changing is actually the same on screen
因此它会尽可能多的重用视图
so it's gonna reuse everything it can
他仍然会重新绘制整个屏幕
it's still gonna redraw the entire screen
但是如果这个操作对你来说是很致命的话
but if that's the really issue for you
你可以直接获取到这个视图,用getChildAt
you can directly grab the view,you can call getChildAt
这个方法要在getFirstVisiblePosition的条件体中
然后调用getChildAt获取到相应的视图
that's (why you) use getFirstVisiblePosition to figure out what's translation between the position and index
然后你就可以对这个View设置图片了,
或者干其他的事情了
and you can just call setImage or whatever you want on the view
如果你想看一个好的例子的话,你可以去
https://github.com/oceancx/shelves这里看我写的源码
if you wanna good example,you should look at the (https://github.com/oceancx/shelves)
这就是我在第一个幻灯片中写的app
this application i showed in one of the first slides
我写了很复杂的代码来支持这种操作,你可以拿去看,
然后自己领悟吧
i have very complex code to support that kind of optimize operation,and you can look at it and see how to do it
那边的
oh,there
我有两个问题(一听就是中国的 ^ ^)
hi,i have two questions
第一个是,我试着在列表中采用相对布局
my first is we tried to use a RelativeLayout for a row in the list
列表似乎对相对布局的某些属性
and it seems to ignore the attributes in the RelativeLayout
好了,哥已经猜到了
uh ha..i know why
实际上,我还把这个问题写进了PPT中
and actually,i put the answer on the one of the slides
你的问题是,你的表项是相对布局,
但是布局的某些属性被忽略掉了.对么
yeah,the problem is that you have a RelativeLayout,and you layout attributes are ignored.right?
这里的原因其实很简单
it's actually something very simple and that's
关于这点文档的说明很烂
documentation for that sucks
这仍然属于我们的失误,我们非常抱歉
and again,that's still our fault,i am very sorry,but
这里,看这个例子
so here,for instance
我们在调用inflate方法时,
我们传入了null作为最后一个参数.
we are calling inflate and we are passing null as the last parameter
这个参数是你反射视图的父视图
null is the parent...the parameter is the parent of the view you're inflating
传入null的话,就相当于你告诉framework.
"我不知道其父视图会是什么"
passing null,you're telling the framework,"well i don't know what the parent gonna be"
那么,当我们不知道父视图是什么的话,
我们就不知道父布局参数的会是什么
now we don't know the parents,we don't know what the layout parameters will be
那么我们就不去获取父视图了,我就忽略掉父视图的参数了
so we just give up,we just don't get the parameter,so
那么你要做的工作就是调用这个版本的inflate
what you have to do is call this version of inflates
在你传入父视图的时候.
这就是为啥getView返回parent参数的原因
when you pass the parents.and that's why in getView() would give you the parent
此时,你把父视图传递进去了,
但是当你第三个参数传入true的话
so you pass the parents,but if pass true at the end
我们就会在父视图中调用addView,
把你要反射的视图加入进去
we gonna call addView() on the parents with the view you're inflating
但是如果你在ListView中这么干的话,ListView会崩溃
所以你不得不传入false
but if you do that on the ListView,it's gonna crash,so you have to pass false
无论何时你在ListView中反射视图的时候,就用这种写法
so whenever you're in getView and you inflate something always pass the parents and false in the (inflate called)
这就会解决掉你的问题了
and that will work
多谢,那么再问一个问题
thank you.my second question
我们试着用字母索引器来辅助快速滚动
we also use...we tried to use a AlphabetIndexer for a fast scrolling
但是如果列表中的数据被改变的话,
似乎索引器不能被更新
and that data does change,it seems like that the AlphabetIndexer can't be updated
是的,这里是有这个限制,这是一个bug
yeah,that's currently (limitation).we have a bug field somewhere (internally)about that
我们可能会去把这个bug给解决了,
但是这似乎在近期内不会实现
maybe we will do it,but i don't think it's gonna happen very soon
如果各位愿意为此写一个代码补丁的话,我会亲自审查
so if you guys want to write a (code patch),i am gonna read you it myself
我会很高兴接受你的补丁
i would be very glad to accept it
多谢
ok.thank you
你刚说你对android的问题知无不言
you said you take questions about Android in general
是的,放马过来
we can try
我现在有点赶时间,因为昨天家里有事儿呼叫我
ok,well,i am playing (catch-up) because family emergency (kept) me out yesterday
Froyo现在会发布吗,Froyo发布时间定了么
has Froyo been addressed or is there words when it will be
我没接到任何通知
nothing has been announced
好的
ok
它是不是已经加入AOSP中了呢
is it true it has hit AOSP already though
我没有接到任何通知
nothing has been announced
好,我问完了
ok
亲
hi
我们很善于躲避类似的问题呢
we have very very good (dodging) in these questions,don't even try
请麦克前的这位发言
the mic first...can you go the mic
这里每个幻灯片都会上传到GoogleIO网站上,
你可以获取到视频以及幻灯片
yes,so the slides.every session within the next few weeks will be available on the Google IO website,you'll get the video and slides
我不清楚
i don't know
好了好了
that's ok
这里我有一个ListView,我的应用中的一部分是
ok,so,i have a ListView,the part of my app is
关于地理服务的,其两个设备之间用到了GPS
it's surveying app i am using a GPS between two devices,so
要说我为啥这么干的话就扯远了
long story it takes exactly what it does when i am doing that for
我就直接切入到ListView的问题吧
just get right the point with the ListView question
这里...
so ...one of the things...
我用到了SMS来收发消息
part of this is i am using sms to send message just back and forth
某人可以把自己的当前位置给发送出去
you can either send...somebody can send them current position
比方说发送当前的GPS坐标,或者可以发送
the current GPS coordinates,or they can send your message says like
这样的移动指令,你可以往右走10码么,等等
could you move like ten yards to the right or something like that
现在我用到了Java的正则表达式
so right now,i am using a java (reg X)
来给某人发送的GPS坐标进行匹配
to sort out between when somebody says your pair GPS coordinates
然后把这些信息填充到ListView中
and populating that in a ListView that has your positional data
这跟刚才你谈到聊天客户端的实现有些不同
(?versus)the chat window...the chat window which has a ListView
在ListView中,你刚刚谈到了一个类
you were talking earlier about a class which
会做一些预测的工作
will do sort of like predictive
这个类会在你输入的时候,对列表进行过滤.
那叫什么来着
it was sort of sorting out of as you're typing or there is data comes in
嗯,这是过滤器类
yeah,it's a filtering
那么我的应用中是用java的RegX更快呢还是用过滤器类呢
i'm wondering,would the filter be more proper with that or am i just better (off) with this the (re-guess) gonna be faster
我认为,你可以对过滤器的实现采用regX,
这完全取决于你的选择
i mean you can implement the Filter with the (reg X),so i mean it's really up to you
好吧
ok
我认为对你的应用来说.这无关紧要
i don't think it matters in your case
好吧,那就是说我不用对regX做任何修改了
ok,it's not...am i getting losing or gaining anything i going to java.regX
不用啊/那好吧
not at all/ ok
多谢了
all right.thanks
这个过滤器是不是最善于做交互用的呢
is the filtering is that mostly for interactive
你也可以把它用在非交互的操作上,但是这又扯远了
yes,you can use it on non-interactive actions,but it's not really matter for that
好的,谢谢
ok,all right,thanks
好的,来看看Dory上的问题
so,question from Dory
对ListView设置适配器可能会使UI线程受阻
setting the adapter to the ListView can become a block operation
如果适配器的数据源是来自网络的话,有啥建议么
if the adapter gets the data from the network,any tips?
请用线程
use threads
哥只能帮你到这儿了
that's pretty much all there is to it
这不会使UI线程受阻
just don't block the UI thread
这里需要注意的是,尽管你在另外的线程中从网络上获取数据
right.again,the trick here to make sure that even if you are collecting your data from the network
你必须在UI线程中执行提交操作
you have to perform the commit operation on the UI thread
你可以对你的UI线程发送一个消息
来通知数据已经获取到
so you can go ahead just post a message to your UI thread through the normal event system
然后把你的最终得到的数据插入到适配器中
and take your big (blob)of data that you have the end
然后把变化提交给适配器,通过调用notifyDatasetChanged
and go ahead and commit changes to the adapter there,call notifyDatasetChanged
我有一个列表
i have a list
我用一个数组为此列表设置了一个列表适配器
that i set the list adapter from an array that i have in my program
点击监听器,大多数情况下,工作的很好.
刚刚你们也谈到了过滤器类
and onClick,most of the time it works just great,i have the position and you guys were talking about filter
我的列表中的数据都有id,我在想
and there is an id,i am wondering
我可以用id来关联我的数组么,同时,
由此获取到的数据的位置还应该是正确的
can i use that id and will it correlate to my array and the position it should be
因为如果用位置去匹配的话,假如说列表中有100项时
cause the position,if there are filters and then there's three items,hundred items in an array,then
选出来的表项就有问题
it picks the wrong item,so
我可以保证获取到那种正确的关联么
can i guarantee (that they'll) correlate
默认情况下,在数组适配器中
so by default,in an ArrayAdapter
表项的id就是你的数组的索引
the id is the index of the item inside of your array
当你对数组适配器进行过滤的时候
it's gonna...so when you filter the ArrayAdapter
这里的id就会变化,使得id不固定
the ids will change,so they are not stable
如果你想让过滤操作不改变id的话,
你就需要自定义适配器
so if you wanna them to be stable across filtering,you have to implement your own adapter
你可以让过滤器存储一些额外的数据在表项中
以便你搞清楚正确的表项是什么
and maybe change the filter to store some extra data in the item,so that you can know what item it is
好的,懂了
ok,ok
根本上来讲,我要做的是对交叉引用数据,然后做检查/是的
so i just basically have to cross reference the data and just check./yeah
好的,谢谢喽
ok.thank you
我们知道这样做不是很棒,但是没办法.
yeah,we know it's not great but sorry
很不幸,我们问答时间已经用完了
and (unfortunately),we are out of time for the questions
因此,如果你有更多的问题的话,
请到Google群组中的Android版块提问
so if you have more questions,we have the Android Google Groups
你也可以在StackOverflow上提问
there are StackOverflow where you can ask questions online
我们团队中有人监视网上提出的问题,
然后会尝试着帮你解决问题
like a few of us are monitoring everything and we will try to answer your questions when we have time
谢谢大家的到场
thank you very much
听完掌声吧
clap
微博求粉:Ocean-藏心.
我也谢谢大家把视频给看完了
thank you for watching.